(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-09-09T22:38:11.162902",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.7-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
配信しました
We're live.
はーい
Okay.
で、配信が来たら…
And once the stream comes up...
あ、来た来た来た
Ah, here it is, here it is.
じゃあBGMお願いします
Alright, queue the BGM, please.
はーい
Got it.
いよーーっ
Iyooo—!
ストレート ドキドキする
Straight on, my heart is pounding.
視線はまるでレーザービーム
Your gaze is just like a laser beam.
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Piercing right into my bubbly heart,
虹色のラブビーム
a rainbow-colored love beam.
実る果実が水を弾いて
As ripening fruits repel the water,
キラキラしてる光に似てる
it resembles a sparkling light.
グラウンドに立つ君の姿が
Your figure standing on the field
眩しくて少し照れちゃうけど
is so dazzling it makes me a little shy, but...
ストレート まっすぐだね
Straight on, so straightforward!
恋愛はきっとレーザービーム
Love is definitely a laser beam.
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Piercing right into my bubbly heart,
虹色のラブビーム
a rainbow-colored love beam.
二人をつなぐ秘密の光
The secret light that connects the two of us,
あの日見つけた秘密の光
the secret light we found on that day.
恋の瞬間 音は止まって
At the moment of love, sound comes to a halt,
時間はスローリーに 恋の光線
and time moves slowly with this beam of love.
ストレート ドキドキする
Straight on, my heart is pounding.
視線はまるでレーザービーム
Your gaze is just like a laser beam.
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Piercing right into my bubbly heart,
虹色のラブビーム
a rainbow-colored love beam.
ストレート まっすぐだね
Straight on, so straightforward!
恋愛はきっとレーザービーム
Love is definitely a laser beam.
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Piercing right into my bubbly heart,
虹色のラブビーム
a rainbow-colored love beam.
いよぉ〜〜っ！
Iyooo...!
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
Gather round, come take a look!
始まりました、らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ！
Raden's new outfit reveal 3D live has begun!
今宵はまだまだこれから！
Tonight is just getting started!
皆さん一緒に盛り上がっていきましょーー！
Let's all get hyped together!
尽きない好奇心
Endless curiosity,
素晴らしきジャポニズムに触れて
touching upon wonderful Japonism.
令和の風雲児
The revolutionary hero of Reiwa,
皆々にお届け致しましょ
let us present it to one and all!
饒舌に情熱
Eloquence with passion,
伝えたい愛に溢れている
overflowing with love I wish to share.
無知の知がきっ​​と
Surely "knowing that you know nothing"
素敵な始まりになるんだよ
will become a wonderful beginning!
知ってほしい
I want you to know,
たらふく味わって
savoring it to your heart's content.
尊い人生
In this precious life,
紐解いた歴史に 心惹かれていく
my heart is captivated by unraveling history.
遥か遠く 電波に乗って あなたまで
Riding the airwaves to reach you far away,
この想い純粋に伝えたい
I want to share these pure feelings.
新しい世界 見せてあげる
I'll show you a brand new world!
開口一番やっちゃって
Getting straight to it right off the bat,
破天荒に型破って 打ち立てる
breaking the mold unprecedentedly and building
金字塔 パンチライン 時を超え
a monumental punchline that transcends time!
出囃子に乗せて
Riding to the debayashi music,
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
gather round, come take a look!
はい！はい！
Hai! Hai!
はい！
Hai!
はい！はい！
Hai! Hai!
はい！
Hai!
浪漫を抱いた人生を
With a life embracing romance,
丸ごと賭けて傾きましょう
let's gamble it all and live boldly!
刹那に生きた足跡を
The footprints lived in fleeting moments,
偉大な先人と共に
together with the great predecessors.
洒落た口火切って
Striking a stylish opening spark,
手招く芸事の深淵
beckoning into the depths of the arts.
相反する感情 愛憎
Opposing emotions, love and hate,
超えていく感動
transcending into moving emotion.
遥か遠く世界超え宇宙まで
Far and wide, crossing the world to the cosmos,
この想い果てしなく届けたい
I want to convey these endless feelings.
オリエンタル オクシデンタル
Oriental, Occidental,
どちらも愛しちゃって
loving them both.
掻き立てる衝動が加速する
Stirring impulses accelerate,
創造の世界へと飛び込んで
leaping into the world of creation.
小噺に乗せて
Set along with a short tale,
寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい
step right up and have a look!
語り継いでく 人世の想い
The feelings passed down across the mortal world,
あなたの心に寄り添って
gently cuddling close to your heart.
道楽主義で小粋にいなせ
Hedonistic, stylish, and gallant,
そんな生き様如何ですか？
how do you fancy living such a way?
遥か遠く電波に乗ってあなたまで
Far and wide, riding the airwaves to reach you,
この想い純粋に伝えたい
I want to convey these purely genuine feelings.
新しい世界見せてあげる
I'll show you a brand new world!
開口一番やっちゃって
Getting right down to it from the very start,
破天荒に型破って打ち立てる
daringly breaking the mold to establish
金字塔パンチライン時を超え
a monumental punchline transcending time.
出囃子に乗せて
Carried upon the entrance music,
寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい
step right up and have a look!
Step right up and have a look!
はい！はい！
Hai! Hai!
はい！
Hai!
はい！はい！
Hai! Hai!
はい、ということで...
Alright, and so...
ということで、始まりました！
And with that, it has begun!
儒烏風亭らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブー！
Juufuutei Raden's New Outfit Reveal 3D Live!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you so much!
はい、皆様改めまして、こんばんは！
Yes, once again everyone, good evening!
ホロライブDEV_ISはReGLOSSの神出鬼没のミュージアムプリンセス担当、
From hololive DEV_IS ReGLOSS, in charge of being the elusive museum princess,
儒烏風亭一門は前座見習い、
and the apprentice opening act of the Juufuutei school,
ちょっと待って...
Wait a second...
儒烏風亭らでんでございますー！
I am Juufuutei Raden!
皆来てくれてありがとうございますー！
Thank you all so much for coming!
本日のハッシュタグは「#らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ」で
If you could post lots with today's hashtag, "#RadenNewOutfitReveal3DLive",
いっぱいポストしてくれると、とっても嬉しいです！よろしくお願いします！
I'd be super happy! Thank you in advance!
ちょっと待って、「大丈夫？」って言われてます。
Wait, people are asking, "Are you okay?"
大丈夫です！ありがとうございます！
I'm okay! Thank you so much!
はい！さあ今回ね、らでん3Dお披露目ライブ...
Alright! So this time, in my 3D reveal live...
新衣装お披露目ライブ「魅惑の重大発表祭り」、
New Outfit Reveal Live "Enchanting Major Announcement Festival",
タイトルにもある通り、何やら重大発表があるとか、ないとか...
as in the title, there may or may not be some major announcements...
しかも、1つだけじゃないの！
And what's more, it's not just one!
ということで、今日はね、是非最後までお楽しみくださーい！
So please be sure to enjoy today's show until the very end!
さあ、そして皆さん、気になってますよね？この新衣装、如何でしょうかー？
Now then, everyone, you're curious, right? What do you think of this new outfit?
デンデケデンデケデンデンデン...
Dun-deke-den-deke-den-den-den...
どう？皆どうかな？
How is it? What do you all think?
これが私、らでんの新衣装「ミュージアムプリンセス衣装」でーす！
This is my, Raden's, new outfit: the "Museum Princess Outfit"!
どう？どうかな？どうかな？どうかな、皆？
How is it? What do you think? How is it, everyone?
ちょっとね、今日ね、ラグがね、ちょっとコメントとのラグがあってね、あれなんですけれども...
There's a bit of a delay with the chat today, so it's a little tricky, but...
良い？良い？ありがとう！ありがとうございます！
You like it? You like it? Thank you! Thank you so much!
かわいい？ありがとう！ありがとうございます！
Cute? Thank you! Thank you so much!
えー、今回ですね、100万人記念ということで、佐倉シオリ先生にお仕立ていただきましたー！
Well, to celebrate reaching 1 million subscribers, it was tailored by Shiori Sakura-sensei!
イェーイ！
Yay!
これもね、普段から応援してくださっている皆様のおかげです！本当にありがとうー！ありがとうございますー！
This is all thanks to everyone who always supports me! Truly, thank you! Thank you so much!
もちろんね、このライブの後、アンコールライブっていうのがメン限であるんですけれども、
Of course, after this live, we'll have an encore live for channel members,
そこでまたのんびりと、このお衣装について詳しくね、見ていきたいと思いますので、
where we can take our time and look at this outfit in detail,
気になるよって...
so for those who are curious...
ぜひ、メンバーシップの方に加入していただければと思います。
I hope you'll consider joining my membership!
今日ね、お昼ぐらいにメンバーの方が使えるスタンプも追加されましたので、
Today around noon, new stamps for members were added as well,
ぜひコメント欄で、よかったら使ってみてください。
so please feel free to try them out in the chat!
もうみんな使いたくてたまらないアロワナスタンプとかが追加されてるんで、
They added stamps everyone's been dying to use, like the arowana stamp,
ぜひ皆さんでね、コメント欄いっぱいアロワナを泳がせてください。よろしくお願いしますー！
so please make lots of arowanas swim in the chat! Thank you!
さあ、ということで、お衣装、改めて新衣装なんですが、
Now then, about this costume—once again, it's my new outfit,
今回、衣装の他に、ちょっとね、ひとつ、とあるものを作りましたよー！
but besides the outfit, I also had something else made!
ま、楽曲中にもね、出てきたんですけれども、
Well, it also appeared during the songs, but...
じゃんじゃかじゃんじゃんじゃんじゃん…あ、あ、逆…じゃーん！
Ta-da-da-da-da-da... Ah, wrong way... Ta-da!
ステッキでございますー！
It's a cane!
いいでしょ、これ？かっこいいでしょ？今回ね、特注でステッキ作っちゃったー！
Isn't this great? Cool, right? I had a custom cane made this time!
しかも、これだけじゃないんですよー。
And what's more, that's not all!
見ててね。
Watch this.
らでんビーム！
Raden Beam!
うわー！レーザービームだー！すごーい！
Whoa! It's a laser beam! Awesome!
今回ね、あの、レーザービームを出せるようにしてもらいました！
This time, they made it able to shoot laser beams!
ヴン、ヴン、ヴン、ヴンヴンヴン…
Vwoom, vwoom, vwoom, vwoom...
もう大丈夫です。疲れちゃった。
That's enough now. I got tired.
いかん、もう今日はね、ライブまだまだこれからですので、体力は温存していかないと。
Oh no, today's live is just getting started, so I have to save my energy.
でも今日は、自分の体力がもう空っぽになるまで、全力でライブするから、みんな応援よろしくねー！
But today, I'm going to give it my all until my stamina runs completely empty, so please cheer me on!
それでは、そろそろ次の曲に行きたいと、思います。
And now, I think it's about time to move on to the next song.
さあ、次の曲は何なのか、重大発表とは何なのか、わくわくしながら聴いてくださいね。
What will the next song be? What is the major announcement? Please listen while anticipating!
そしてここからは、ゲストも登場します！
And from here on, guests will be appearing!
ゲストパートは収録になりますので、悪しからず！
The guest segment is pre-recorded, so please keep that in mind!
それでは、今宵はまだまだ始まったばかり！みんなで一緒に楽しみましょう！
Tonight has only just begun! Let's all have fun together!
それでは、どうぞー！
Here we go!
そう高く果てなく
So high and endlessly
明日へと導くよ
Leading towards tomorrow
私だけの光放ちたい
I want to radiate my own light
DIVE!
WOW...
自信なくしてただ心に鍵かけて
Losing confidence, just locking up my heart
響く自分の声に耳塞いでた
Covering my ears to my own echoing voice
ホントはいつだってわかっていたんだよ
But the truth is, I always knew
一番大切なものここにあること
That the most important thing is right here
無限に広がる宇宙 迷わず進もう
An infinitely expanding sky, let's move forward without hesitation
Go! Fly!
Yes! So High!
目を閉じて言い聞かせてみたってもう
Even if I close my eyes and try telling myself,
身体中騒いでる 止まらないHeart
My whole body is racing, an unstoppable heart
強く熱く…！
Strong and passionate...!
そう高く果てなく
So high and endlessly
抱きしめた未来が軌跡になる
The future I embraced becomes my path
生まれた思いが明日へと導くよ
The feelings born inside lead me towards tomorrow
私だけの光放ちたい
I want to radiate my own light
DIVE!
WOW...
誰のものでもない心に問いかけて
Asking my heart, which belongs to no one else
選んだ道の先へとまっすぐに
Heading straight toward the end of the path I chose
どんな時だって見失わないよ
No matter when, I won't lose sight of it
一番大切な場所を見つけたから
Because I found the most precious place
遠回りでもいい 胸張って進もう
Even if it's a detour, let's proudly march forward
Louder!
Sing! Louder!
不器用かな でも傷ついたって構わないよ
Maybe I'm clumsy, but I don't care if I get hurt
曇りない気持ちで生きたい Pride 私らしく…！
I want to live with a clear heart, my pride, true to myself...!
両手を広げて
Spreading both my hands wide
解き放した昨日が翼になる
The yesterday I unleashed becomes wings
重ねた出会いが…
The encounters we've gathered...
この瞬間に踊るよ
I'll dance in this very moment
私だけの光 信じて
believing in my own unique light!
DIVE!
そう高く 果てなく
So high, boundlessly,
抱きしめた未来が 奇跡になる
the future I embraced will become a miracle.
生まれた想いが
These feelings that were born
明日へと導くよ
will guide me toward tomorrow.
私だけの光 放ちたい
I want to shine my own unique light!
DIVE!
WOW WOW WOW
JAPANの美術史♪ (アート！アート！)
JAPAN's art history♪ (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (絵画に立体！)
JAPAN's art history♪ (Paintings and sculptures!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (テストもバッチリ！)
JAPAN's art history♪ (Acing the tests!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！
Let's memorize it SHOW!
さあ、3Dライブの途中ではございますが、ここで日本美術史の授業を始めたいと思います！
Now then, right in the middle of our 3D live, I'd like to begin our Japanese art history class!
は〜いみなさんこんにちは！美術史を学ぶ時間です！
Hello everyone! It's time to learn art history!
まずは縄文弥生古墳まで やってみよう
First, let's cover from Jomon and Yayoi to Kofun!
火焔型土器、遮光器土偶、縄文のビーナス！
Flame-style pottery, goggle-eyed dogu, Venus of Jomon!
銅鐸、銅戈、銅矛、銅剣、弥生土器
Dotaku bells, bronze daggers, spears, swords, Yayoi pottery!
埴輪も色々、踊る人々、掛甲武人、馬型埴輪
Various Haniwa, dancing figures, armored warriors, horse Haniwa!
古墳出土の鉄刀、鉄剣、七支刀に土師器須恵器
Iron blades and swords from Kofun, Seven-Branched Sword, Haji and Sue pottery!
OK OK OK OKいい感じ！
OK OK OK OK, looking good!
次は飛鳥に奈良時代！さん！に！いち！
Next up is Asuka and Nara periods! 3! 2! 1!
ゴー！
GO!
仏像いっぱい釈迦如来、菩薩と合わせて三尊像
Lots of Buddha statues, Shaka Nyorai, paired with Bodhisattvas for the Triad!
玉虫厨子、天寿国繍帳、金堂壁画、古墳壁画
Tamamushi Shrine, Tenjukoku Shucho, Kondo murals, Kofun murals!
東大寺には奈良の大仏、興福寺には阿修羅像
Todaiji has the Great Buddha of Nara, Kohfukuji has the Ashura statue!
音と一緒に遊びましょう！螺鈿紫檀五絃琵琶
Let's play along with the sound! Five-stringed rosewood biwa with raden inlay!
未来のキミに届くように 繋いでいこう この想い
So that it reaches the future you, let's keep passing on these feelings
愛さえあれば大丈夫 語り合おう 朝が来るまで
As long as there's love, it'll be fine; let's talk until morning comes!
JAPANの美術史♪ (アート！アート！)
JAPAN's art history♪ (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (絵画に立体！)
JAPAN's art history♪ (Paintings and sculptures!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (テストもバッチリ！)
JAPAN's art history♪ (Acing the tests!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！
Let's memorize it SHOW!
まだまだ色々ございます。がんばってついてきてくださいね！
There's still so much more! Do your best to keep up, okay?
平安鎌倉南北朝 参る
Heian, Kamakura, Nanboku-cho, here we go!
曼荼羅、一木造、寄木造
Mandala, single-block carving, joined-block carving!
鳥獣人物戯画に源氏物語
Choju-jinbutsu-giga and The Tale of Genji!
平等院鳳凰堂阿弥陀如来坐像
Byodoin Phoenix Hall's Seated Statue of Amida Nyorai!
模様がとってもかわいい 片輪車螺鈿手箱！
With such a cute pattern: Carriage-wheel raden cosmetic box!
東大寺の南大門の金剛力士像
The Nio guardian statues at Todaiji's Great South Gate!
阿弥陀二十五菩薩来迎図、山越阿弥陀図
Descent of Amida and 25 Bodhisattvas, Mountain-Crossing Amida!
蒙古襲来絵詞、空也上人像
Illustrated Account of the Mongol Invasion, Kuya Shonin statue!
一遍上人絵伝、後三年合戦絵巻
Illustrated Biography of Monk Ippen, Picture Scroll of the Later Three Years' War!
YOYO！半分くらい来たぜ多分！
Yo, yo! We're about halfway through, probably!
まだまだいくぜ、ありのまま！室町から安土桃山！
Still keeping it going, as it is! From Muromachi to Azuchi-Momoyama!
能面翁に枯山水
Noh Okina mask and dry landscape garden!
天橋立図、呂洞賓図、狩野派の屏風！
View of Amanohashidate, Lu Dongbin, Kano School folding screens!
曜変天目茶碗
Yohen Tenmoku tea bowl!
洛中洛外図屏風、唐獅子図屏風、松鷹図
Scenes in and around Kyoto, Chinese Lions, Pine and Hawk screens!
職人尽図、花下遊楽図、松林図、山水図
Depiction of Craftsmen, Merrymaking Under the Blossoms, Pine Trees, Landscapes!
八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱 (えっ、これ本物！？えー！)
Eight-plank bridge maki-e raden inkstone box! (Wait, is this real?! Whoa!)
未来のキミに届くように 繋いでいこう この想い
So that it reaches the future you, let's keep passing on these feelings
愛さえあれば大丈夫 語り合おう 朝が来るまで
As long as there's love, it'll be fine; let's talk until morning comes!
なんと今回特別に！バーチャル八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱さんに
And today, as a special treat, Virtual Eight-plank Bridge Maki-e Raden Inkstone Box-san
来ていただきました！ありがとうございますー！
has joined us! Thank you so much!
あとちょっと、最後まで頑張ろう！江戸時代から昭和まで！行きますよ！
Just a little more, let's do our best till the end! From the Edo period to Showa! Here we go!
さん！に！いち！ゴー！
3! 2! 1! GO!
舟橋蒔絵硯箱、風神雷神図屏風
Pontoon Bridge maki-e inkstone box, Wind God and Thunder God screens!
燕子花図屏風、見返り美人
Irises folding screens, Beauty Looking Back!
好色一代男
The Life of an Amorous Man...
奥の細道
The Narrow Road to the Deep North
富嶽三十六景、
Thirty-Six Views of Mount Fuji,
東海道中膝栗毛
Tokaidochu Hizakurige,
老猿、ゆあみ、坑夫
Old Monkey, Bathing, Miner,
墓守、伎芸天
Gravedigger, Gigeiten,
竜虎図、黒き猫
Dragon and Tiger, Black Cat,
鮭、海の幸
Salmon, Harvest of the Sea,
渡頭の夕暮
Dusk at the Ferry,
麗子微笑、紫禁城
Smiling Reiko, Forbidden City,
斑猫、五浦釣人
Tabby Cat, Angler of Izura,
太陽の塔
Tower of the Sun,
吉原治良の円
Jiro Yoshihara's Circle,
東山魁夷の道
Kai Higashiyama's The Road
未来のキミに届くように
So it may reach you in the future,
繋いでいこう この想い
let's pass on these feelings!
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there is love, we'll be fine,
語り合おう 朝が来るまで
let's talk through the night until morning comes,
未来まで
all the way into the future!
最後！JAPANの美術史♪（アート！アート！）
One last time! Japan's art history! (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史♪（絵画に立体！）
Japan's art history! (Paintings and sculptures!)
JAPANの美術史♪（テストもバッチリ！）
Japan's art history! (Perfect for tests too!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！
Let's-learn-it-SHOW!
ありがとーう！
Thank you so much!
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんは！
To everyone watching the live stream, good evening!
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここで、らでんの小噺美術解説のお時間でーーーす！
We are mid-concert, but it's now time for Raden's Art Commentary Tidbits!
なんと、今回ご紹介するのは、こちらでん！
Amazingly, what I'll be presenting today is this-den!
ジャジャーン！
Ta-daaa!
国宝、八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱！ということで、
The National Treasure: 'Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Suzuribako'! So,
今回、特別に東京国立博物館さんから3Dモデルをお借りしましたーーー！
for this occasion, we were specially loaned this 3D model from the Tokyo National Museum!
よいしょ。みんなにもよく見てもらいましょう。こちらでございます！
Up we go. Let's give everyone a closer look. Here it is!
こちらが、バーチャル八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱です！
This is the Virtual Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Suzuribako!
螺鈿ってなんかどっかで聞いたことがありますね。なんかそんな名前のバーチャルYouTuberがいるような、いなかったような…
'Raden'... sounds like I've heard that somewhere before. Like there's a VTuber by that name, or maybe not...
こちらは私のオリジナル曲『JAPANの美術史♪お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！』にも登場する作品です。
This is an artwork that also appeared in my original song, 'JAPAN's Art History: Let's-Learn-It SHOW!'
どうですか皆さん、この輝きとデザイン！
What do you think, everyone? Look at this radiance and design!
大胆、かつ花びらの装飾の細かい部分も美しいこちらの作品、作ったのは尾形光琳という人です。
Bold, yet with beautifully detailed flower petal decorations, this piece was created by someone named Ogata Korin.
彼がこの硯箱を作ったのは江戸時代なんですが、どこかモダンな様子も感じることができます。
He created this inkstone writing box during the Edo period, but you can feel a somewhat modern aesthetic to it.
さて、工芸品を見るとき様々な見方がありますが、手助けになるのは作品名です。ではスライド行きます！
Now, while there are many ways to appreciate crafts, the artwork's title is a big help. Let's move to the slide!
えー、この工芸品の名前復習しましょう。八橋、蒔絵、螺鈿、硯箱。
Let's review the name of this craft: 'Yatsuhashi', 'Makie', 'Raden', 'Suzuribako'.
漢字がたくさん入っていますが、一つ一つ紐解いていきます。
It contains a lot of kanji, but let's break them down one by one.
まずは八橋。
First is 'Yatsuhashi'.
日本美術史における工芸品は、物語の一場面や和歌、歌ですね、がテーマになっていることが少なくありません。
In Japanese art history, decorative crafts often take scenes from literary tales or waka poems as their themes.
そしてこの硯箱もその一つ。
And this writing box is one of them.
『伊勢物語』第九段、三河国八橋の場面が主題になっているんですよ。
The subject here is the scene at Yatsuhashi in Mikawa Province from Section 9 of 'The Tales of Ise'.
なのでこれは橋ですね。
So this represents the bridge.
八橋、この場面に出てくる8つの橋のこと。
'Yatsuhashi' refers to the eight-plank bridge appearing in that scene.
つまりは、何を描いたかを表しています。
In other words, it indicates what is depicted.
では、何を描いたかが分かったら次にどんな技法が使われたか。
Now that we know what is depicted, next is what techniques were used.
それを表すのが蒔絵、そして螺鈿です。
That is represented by 'Makie' and 'Raden'.
蒔絵とは簡単に言うと、金の粉を漆という接着剤を用いて貼り付けたもの。
To put it simply, makie is decorating with gold powder affixed using lacquer (urushi) as an adhesive.
ここで言うと杜若の葉っぱの部分ですね。ぴょんぴょんってなってる部分です。
In this piece, it's the leaves of the rabbit-ear irises—these parts springing up.
次に螺鈿とは、貝の光沢を持つ部分を薄くして貼り付けたもの。
Next, raden is a technique where thin slices of lustrous seashell are inlaid.
ここで言うと、杜若のお花の部分です！
In this case, it's the iris flowers!
この作品に使われているのはアワビ貝で、花びらを表現するためにあえて穴の空いた貝を使用しているのが分かります。
Abalone shells are used here, and we can see that shells with natural holes were deliberately chosen to depict the petals.
そして最後に、そもそもこれは何化？それを表すのが硯箱です。
And finally, what actually is this object? That's what 'Suzuribako' (writing box) tells us.
えー、真ん中ご覧ください。こちら、墨汁を作る硯入れが上の段にあり、
Take a look at the center. Here on the upper tray, there's a holder for the inkstone used to make ink,
さらにその段の下、下の段は料紙、紙入れになっています。
and below that, the lower tier serves as a paper container for stationery.
さあ、これで「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」の言葉の紐解きが完了しましたね。
And with that, we've broken down every word in 'Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Suzuribako'!
杜若が咲く川にかかる橋のダイナミックな魅力にも大注目なこの硯箱、
Featuring the dynamic charm of a bridge spanning a river with blooming irises,
パカッと開けると、波が描かれています。
when you pop this writing box open, waves are depicted inside.
もうここまで聞いたら、なぜそこに波の意匠を施したのか皆さんならお分かりですね。
Having heard this much, I'm sure you all understand why a wave motif was applied there.
上の段にある橋の、下の…
Beneath the bridge situated on the upper tier...
波...
Waves...
ということですねー
...that's what it is.
実はですね こちらの八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱
Actually, this Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Suzuribako...
普段展示される際は 箱を閉じた状態なんですよ
is usually displayed with the box closed when exhibited.
つまり 中の様子をご覧いただけるのは
In other words, getting to see inside like this...
この配信ならではの貴重な機会です！
...is a rare opportunity unique to this stream!
こちらがなんと 2026年5月26日から
This will surprisingly be exhibited from May 26...
8月16日 本館2室にて展示されるとのことで
...to August 16, 2026, in Room 2 of the Main Building,
東京国立博物館さんでぜひ見てみていただければと思いまーす！
so please go check it out at the Tokyo National Museum!
この波のね 細かいところがね これ筆でやってるんですからね
The fine details of the waves are done with a brush, you know.
筆でこうやって...
Like this with a brush...
あ お時間となってしまいました
Ah, time is up!
それでは皆さん また次回お会いしましょう！
Well then everyone, see you next time!
特報 その①
[Special Announcement Part 1]
未来の君に届くように 繋いでいこう この想い
To reach the future you, let's connect these feelings
愛さえあれば大丈夫 語り合おう 朝が来るまで
As long as there is love, it'll be fine; let's talk until morning comes
ということで なんと！
And so, amazingly...
私 儒烏風亭らでんと
a collaboration between me, Juufuutei Raden,
東京国立博物館さんとのコラボが決定しましたー！
and the Tokyo National Museum has been confirmed!
すごーい！みんな やったよー！
Amazing! Everyone, we did it!
もうね らでん配信とか色んなところで 東博さんがずっと大好きだって言ってたんですけど
I've always talked on my streams and everywhere about how much I love Tohaku,
今回ね 念願の東博・らでんコラボでございますー！
and now, our long-awaited Tohaku and Raden collaboration is here!
すごーい！
Awesome!
あら？東博... 最近名前聞きましたね
Oh? Tohaku... you've heard that name recently, haven't you?
そうです！先日ね 10月から京都 1月から東京にて開催予定の特別展
That's right! The other day, for the special exhibition scheduled from October in Kyoto and January in Tokyo,
『源氏物語 王朝のかがやき』展の音声ガイドのスペシャルトラックを務めさせていただくことが発表されましたが
it was announced that I will do a special track on the audio guide for "The Tale of Genji: Radiant Culture of the Japanese Imperial Court",
これね これチラシね
and here's the flyer!
なんと この特別展『源氏物語』展の東京会場となる 東京国立博物館さんとも...
And amazingly, with Tokyo National Museum, the Tokyo venue for "The Tale of Genji"...
ごめんなさい！
sorry!
東京国立博物館様とのコラボが決定いたしましたー！すごーい！
a collaboration with Tokyo National Museum has been confirmed! Incredible!
開催時期はこの『源氏物語』展と同じ 2027年1月に実施予定となっておりまーす！
It's scheduled to take place in January 2027, at the same time as "The Tale of Genji" exhibition!
なんで こっちは『源氏物語』展・儒烏風亭らでんコラボ
So, on one hand, we have "The Tale of Genji" × Juufuutei Raden collab,
そして同じ1月に 東京国立博物館・儒烏風亭らでんコラボがあると！
and in that same January, the Tokyo National Museum × Juufuutei Raden collab!
もっと簡単に言うと 来年の1月は東博の色んな所にらでんちゃんが出没しちゃいまーす！っていう感じですー！
To put it simply, next January, Raden-chan will be popping up all over Tohaku!
こちら詳細はですね また続報をお待ちいただければと思いまーす！
Please look forward to future updates for the details on this!
すごいでしょう！すごいすごい！
Isn't it amazing?! Awesome, awesome!
ということで本日の重大発表1つ目は 東博・儒烏風亭らでんコラボでございましたー！
So the first major announcement today was the Tohaku × Juufuutei Raden collaboration!
みんなありがとー！
Thank you, everyone!
さあ ライブも重大発表もまだまだ続きます！
Now, both the live show and major announcements will keep on coming!
ちょっと待って... ちょっと疲れちゃった
Hold on a sec... I got a little tired.
ということでね 東博 元々らでんが日本美術史に興味を持ったのって 東博さんで能面を見て
So regarding Tohaku, the reason I first became interested in Japanese art history was seeing Noh masks there,
その時に「ああ なんて美しいんだ」って思ったし
and back then, I thought, "Ah, how beautiful,"
「らでんて日本で生まれ育ったのに 日本のこと本当に何も知らないんだな」って思ったのがきっかけで
and realized, "Even though I grew up in Japan, I really know nothing about it," which started it all.
そっから なんやかんやあって日本美術史勉強したりして
From there, one thing led to another and I studied Japanese art history,
なんやかんやあってホロライブに入って
one thing led to another and I joined Hololive,
なんやかんやあって今この素敵なお衣装をお披露目して
one thing led to another and now I'm showing off this wonderful outfit,
なんやかんやあってこんなありがたいコラボをさせていただけることになりましたー！
and one thing led to another, leading to this incredible collaboration opportunity!
みんなのおかげだよ ありがとー！
It's all thanks to everyone, thank you!
もう人生本当に何が起こるか分かりません！
You really never know what will happen in life!
もうとんでもない 何がどう未来へ繋がっていくのかみたいなことも もう分かりません
It's unbelievable... you can never predict how things will connect to the future.
人生は奇妙な冒険みたいなもんでございますな！
Life is like a bizarre adventure, isn't it!
さあ ということでそろそろ次の曲に行きたいと思いまーす！
Now then, it's about time to move on to the next song!
それでは聴いてください 『ココロパズルリズム』
Please listen: "Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm".
ハー...
Ah...
ああー
Ah~
ココロのパズル
The puzzle of the heart...
ココロのリズム
The rhythm of the heart...
ココロのパズル
The puzzle of the heart...
ココロのリズム
The rhythm of the heart...
これからの未来
From here on into the future,
ほら たくさんのピース
look, all these many pieces,
組み立てるのは キミ次第
putting them together is entirely up to you.
一つずつの
One by one,
明日を生きる
living each tomorrow,
ココロのパズルとリズム
the puzzle and rhythm of the heart.
うまくは言えないけど
I can't put it into words well, but
不思議と安心して
this strangely reassuring feeling
いられる感覚って
that makes me feel at ease,
まるでパズルみたいだ
it's just like a puzzle.
もうずっと前から
Since a long time ago,
僕らは予約席
we've been reserved seats.
さあ両手つないで
Come on, let's hold hands,
きっと一つになれる
and we can surely become one.
完成が見えていても
Even if we can see the finished picture,
すんなりとはいかないね
it doesn't go smoothly, does it?
それぞれが夢のカケラだね
Each and every one is a piece of a dream.
これからの未来
From here on into the future,
ほら たくさんのピース
look, all these many pieces,
組み立てるのは キミ次第
putting them together is entirely up to you.
一つずつの
One by one,
明日を生きる
living each tomorrow,
空いた隙間を埋める
filling in the open gaps.
楽しいこともきっとあるけど
There will surely be fun times too, but
それよりも大切なのは
even more important than that
悲しかったり
is when we're sad,
嬉しいときに
or when we're happy,
一緒に泣ける そんなココロのパズル
being able to cry together—that's the puzzle of the heart.
すんなりとはいかないね
It doesn't always go so smoothly,
キミと僕のパズルの行方も
even where our puzzle is heading.
これからのLOVE STORY
From here on, our love story,
ほら たくさんのピース
look, all these many pieces,
間違えることもあるけど
we might make mistakes sometimes, but
胸に刻み
etching them into our hearts,
明日を生きる
living each tomorrow,
空いた隙間を埋める
filling in the open gaps.
楽しいこともきっとあるけど
There will surely be fun times too, but
それよりも大切なのは
even more important than that
悲しかったり
is when we're sad,
嬉しいときに
or when we're happy,
一緒に泣ける そんなココロのリズム
being able to cry together—that's the rhythm of the heart.
don't cry don't cry
Walk hand in hand
Ah ah
繋いで
Hold hands,
it's a nice day
これからの未来
From here on into the future,
ほら たくさんのピース
look, all these many pieces,
組み立てるのは キミ次第
putting them together is entirely up to you.
一つずつの
One by one,
明日を生きる
living each tomorrow,
空いた隙間を埋める
filling in the open gaps.
楽しいこともきっとあるけど
There will surely be fun times too, but
それよりも大切なのは
even more important than that
悲しかったり
is when we're sad,
嬉しいときに
or when we're happy,
一緒に泣ける そんなココロのパズル
being able to cry together—that's the puzzle of the heart.
ココロのリズム
The rhythm of the heart.
ああー
Ah~
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんは！
Good evening to everyone watching the live stream!
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここで、らでんの小噺美術解説のお時間でーす！
We're right in the middle of the concert, but now it's time for Raden's Short Art Commentary talk!
今回ご紹介するのは…
What I'll be introducing this time is...
こちらでん！
This piece right here-den!
ジャジャーン！
Ta-da!
クロード・モネ『睡蓮の池』。
Claude Monet, "The Water-Lily Pond."
今回なんとロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんより画像をお借りしております！
This time, we have actually borrowed the image from The National Gallery in London!
本当にありがとうございます！
Thank you so very much!
皆さんどうですか？
Everyone, what do you think?
私、モネの描く世界が大好きなんです！
I absolutely love the world that Monet paints!
まあ、モネといえば日本でもとても人気の高い画家ですが、
Well, speaking of Monet, he is a very popular painter in Japan too,
彼の絵画の魅力はどのようなところにあるのでしょうか？
but what exactly makes his paintings so captivating?
今回は彼の絵画に内在する魅力を言語化していきましょー！
This time, let's put into words the charm inherent in his paintings!
この作品は1899年頃描かれました。
This piece was painted around 1899.
緑色の光があふれる睡蓮の池には大きな橋がかかり、
Across the water-lily pond overflowing with green light spans a large bridge,
橋の奥には柳が描かれています。
and behind the bridge, willows are depicted.
実はこの場所、モネの自宅に作った池なんです。
Actually, this place is a pond that Monet built at his own home.
フランスのジヴェルニーという町に家を購入した彼は、
Having purchased a house in the town of Giverny, France,
近隣の川から水を引いて、自分の理想とする庭を作りました。
he drew water from a nearby river and created his ideal garden.
アーチ状の大きな橋、これ、いわゆる太鼓橋と呼ばれる橋と柳。
The large arching bridge—what is known as an arched bridge—and the willows...
あれ？何だか日本っぽさを感じませんか？
Wait, doesn't it feel somewhat Japanese?
それもそのはず。
And that's no surprise.
彼は日本の浮世絵に強く影響を受けた画家でした。
He was a painter heavily influenced by Japanese ukiyo-e.
彼の描く絵は光にあふれていて、目の前で風が吹いて水面が揺れているようにも見えます。
His paintings are filled with light, looking as if the wind is blowing and ripples are swaying right before our eyes.
じーっと見ていると、水も花も木も橋も空気でさえも溶けていくようです。
As you gaze at it, the water, flowers, trees, bridge, and even the air seem to melt together.
見ていて落ち着く絵画だと思いませんか？
Don't you think it's such a soothing painting to look at?
モネは絵を描くとき、色を混ぜて塗るのではなく、
When Monet painted, rather than mixing colors on the palette,
純粋な何も混ざってない色を置くように塗りました。
he applied pure, unmixed colors as if placing them side by side.
色は混ぜれば混ぜるほど、塗り重ねれば重ねるほど暗くなっていきます。
The more you mix colors or layer them over each other, the darker they become.
彼はこの課題を「色を置く」ことによって解決し、光であふれた絵画の表現に成功したんです。
He solved this issue by "placing" color, succeeding in expressing paintings overflowing with light.
この絵画に近づいて見ると、筆跡がしっかり残っています。
Looking closely at this painting, the brushstrokes remain distinctly visible.
隣り合った絵の具一つひとつの相乗効果を計算し、
Calculating the synergistic effect of each adjacent paint stroke,
絵の具の塊から温度感や湿度感を感じることができる風景へと変貌する表現は、モネが生涯かけて研究していたものです。
the expression of turning paint blobs into a landscape where you can feel the temperature and humidity was what Monet studied throughout his entire life.
光を求めたモネが陰影のない日本の浮世絵に強く惹かれたのも理解できますね。
It's easy to understand why Monet, who sought light, was so drawn to shadowless Japanese ukiyo-e.
彼の絵画の明るさは画家としての研究の成果であり、情熱さえ感じられるそんな作品だと私は感じます。
The brightness of his paintings is the fruit of his artistic research; I feel it's a piece where you can truly sense his passion.
みんなはこの絵画どう読んだかな？
How did all of you interpret this painting?
実はモネは「印象派」の画家と呼ばれるきっかけを作った人でもあるんですが、
Actually, Monet is also the person who gave rise to the term "Impressionism",
それはまた別のお話。
but that is a story for another time.
という感じのことでございまして、こちらはロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんにて見ることができます！
So with that said, you can see this piece at The National Gallery in London!
ぜひ行ってみてくださーい！
Please definitely go visit!
また次回！
See you next time!
(I want to fight your brother)
Let's kung-fu!
Every night I look to the skies and wonder what we did
Always a naive point of view that breaks us in the end
If I could find the meaning of it all I'd take the chance
Maybe in time we'll walk the mile and change it if we can
It's now and always
(How did we get this far na~)
Always
(Just a brand new start na~)
(Never hold me down na~)
Always
Wave goodbye to me!
Around the world 新しいことに
Around the world, to something new,
Around the world フミダスチカラで
Around the world, with the strength to step forward,
Around the world 世界は変わるさ
Around the world, the world will change!
But don't run away 'cause if it's not OK!
I'll change that world into something better honey!
Let's kung-fu!
果てしなく広がる
Stretching out endlessly,
この大地を僕らはまた
across this vast land, we will once again...
僕らはまた 歩き続けるさ
We will keep on walking across this vast land.
全ての意味が 分かるのならば
If we could understand the meaning of it all,
この瞳で 何を見つめるのだろう
what would we gaze upon with these eyes?
IT'S NOW AND ALWAYS
(HOW DID WE GET THIS FAR DID WE GET THIS FAR NA~)
(HOW DID WE GET THIS FAR, DID WE GET THIS FAR, NOW?)
ALWAYS
(WE'RE MAKING A BRAND NEW START JUST A BRAND NEW START NA~)
(WE'RE MAKING A BRAND NEW START, JUST A BRAND NEW START, NOW)
ALWAYS
(NOTHING WILL HOLD ME DOWN NEVER HOLD ME DOWN NA~)
(NOTHING WILL HOLD ME DOWN, NEVER HOLD ME DOWN, NOW)
ALWAYS
WAVE GOODBYE TO ME!
AROUND THE WORLD 君だけのために
AROUND THE WORLD, just for you,
AROUND THE WORLD 探し続けるよ
AROUND THE WORLD, I will keep searching
AROUND THE WORLD 奇跡のかけらを
AROUND THE WORLD for pieces of miracles.
BUT DON'T RUN AWAY 'CAUSE IF IT'S NOT OK!
Yeah ey AND YOU KNOW IT'S GONNA BE RAINING
AND YOU KNOW IT'S GONNA BE HARD
AS LONG AS WE TRUST EACH OTHER
NOTHING'S GONNA BREAK APART OH NO! NO!
IF YA WANNA BE SOMEBODY
GET UP ON YA FEET AND GO
I KNOW WE'RE GONNA MEET EACH OTHER
SOMEWHERE AROUND THE GLOBE
AROUND THE WORLD いつでも自分に
AROUND THE WORLD, those who always
AROUND THE WORLD 負けている人は
AROUND THE WORLD lose to themselves
AROUND THE WORLD 何も掴めない
AROUND THE WORLD will grasp nothing.
BUT DON'T RUN AWAY 'CAUSE IF IT'S NOT OK!
I'LL CHANGE THAT WORLD INTO SOMETHING BETTER HONEY!
特報 その②
[Special Announcement Part 2]
儒烏風亭らでん × THE NATIONAL GALLERY LONDON
[Juufuutei Raden × The National Gallery, London]
儒烏風亭らでん ロンドン ナショナル・ギャラリー コラボ決定!!
[Juufuutei Raden × London National Gallery Collaboration Confirmed!!]
はるばる東京見物行って あたま山で
Traveling from afar to sightsee in Tokyo, at Atamayama!
この想い十全に伝えたい
I want to convey these feelings fully!
新しい世界 見せてあげる
I'll show you a brand new world!
景気一番やっちゃって
Let's liven things up at top energy,
風神に風吹いて 打ち果てる
winds blowing on the Wind God, blowing them away!
錦絵とバージライン 時を超え
Nishiki-e and barge lines, transcending time!
手拍子に乗せて 寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい
Clapping to the rhythm, gather 'round and come take a look!
はい！
Alright!
ということで なんと私 儒烏風亭らでんと...
And so, incredibly, I, Juufuutei Raden, and...
ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとの コラボが決定しましたー！
have officially confirmed a collaboration with The National Gallery in London!
ナショナル・ギャラリーさんと言えば モネ、ゴッホ、ターナー、
Speaking of the National Gallery, they house Monet, Van Gogh, Turner,
もうとにかく色んな画家さんたちの 超有名な作品をいっぱい所蔵されているところなんですが、
and tons of ultra-famous artworks from all kinds of painters,
なんとそんなナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボ！
and amazingly, we're doing a collaboration with that very National Gallery!
『儒烏風亭らでんの瞳に映る 世界の名画』
"Masterpieces of the World Through the Eyes of Juufuutei Raden"
あ、「A SHARED ART JOURNEY」
Ah, "A SHARED ART JOURNEY,"
コラボ決定です！すごーい！
the collaboration is confirmed! Amazing!
さあ これね とある3つの名画とコラボしてるんですが、
Now, this is a collaboration with three specific masterpieces,
皆分かるかな〜？
can you guys tell which ones?
3つね 3つあるんだけど。
There are three of them!
え では左からいきましょうか。
Well then, shall we go from the left?
え 左 ターナー『雨、蒸気、速度―グレート・ウェスタン鉄道』
On the left is Turner's "Rain, Steam, and Speed - The Great Western Railway,"
そして真ん中 モネの『睡蓮の池』
and in the middle is Monet's "The Water-Lily Pond,"
そして一番右 これは皆さんお分かりでしょう ゴッホの『ひまわり』！
and on the far right, which I'm sure you all recognize, is Van Gogh's "Sunflowers"!
そして今回 え コラボ商品がございます！全8種類あるんですよ。
And this time, we have collaboration goods! There are 8 types in total.
じゃあ 1つずつね ちょっと紹介していきましょう。ドーン！
So let me introduce them one by one. Ta-da!
はい！えー まず左上からいきましょうか。
Yes! Um, let's start from the top left.
まずは「フレグランスミストセット」です。
First is the "Fragrance Mist Set."
らでんが監修・考案したフレグランスミスト 3点の名画が持つイメージを香りで表現しました！
For this fragrance mist supervised and designed by me, we expressed the imagery of the three masterpieces through scent!
本商品はアルコールフリーのフレグランスミストなので 色んな場面に合わせて使用可能です。
Since it is an alcohol-free fragrance mist, you can use it in various situations.
じゃあ 隣いきましょうか。
Now, let's move to the one next to it.
えー その隣 「ローラーボールペン」。
Next to that is the "Rollerball Pen."
3つの名画のエッセンスと 儒烏風亭らでんの家紋を見事に融合させたデザインでございます。
It's a design that exquisitely merges the essence of the three masterpieces with my family crest.
えー じゃあ次は左下。
Okay, next is bottom left.
え 「カップ＆ソーサーセット」。
The "Cup & Saucer Set."
描き下ろしたイラストからインスピレーションを得た ボーンチャイナ製のカップ＆ソーサーセットでございます。
Inspired by the newly drawn illustrations, this is a bone china cup & saucer set.
ソーサーの中心には儒烏風亭らでんの名前も記載されています。
Juufuutei Raden's name is also inscribed in the center of the saucer.
最近らでんも紅茶飲めるようになったんで お揃いにしましょうや。
Lately, I've started drinking black tea too, so let's match!
えー そしてその隣が「スカーフ」！
And next to that is the "Scarf"!
新たに描き下ろしたイラスト要素を組み合わせ...
Combining elements from the newly drawn illustrations...
ファッション性と実用性を兼ね備えたデザインスカーフでございます。
A stylish and practical designer scarf.
そして、じゃあその隣行こうか。
And next, moving over...
アクリルスタンド。本コラボならではの新衣装を身にまとうアクリルスタンドでございます。
Acrylic stands! Featuring the new outfit unique to this collaboration.
じゃあ右上行きましょう。キャンバスアート。描き下ろしイラストを使用されるキャンバスアートでございます。
Now let's head to the top right. Canvas art! Canvas art featuring newly drawn illustrations.
その下はトートバッグ。
Below that is the tote bag.
表面には本コラボのために描き下ろされたイラスト、
It features newly drawn illustrations on the front,
裏面には3点の名画のディティールをあしらったデザインの両面仕様となっています。
and details from three masterpieces on the back for a double-sided design.
そして最後、ランダムクリアカードになります。
And finally, we have random clear cards.
全6種のランダムクリアカードで、一部のカードには箔押しデジタルサインと、
Out of 6 random clear cards, some include foil-stamped digital signatures
特別メッセージが入っていますよー！
and special messages!
グッズいいでしょう？どれも素敵でしょう？
Aren't they great? They're all wonderful, right?
そして、さらに！グッズだけではございません！
And what's more... it's not just merchandise!
ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボで、音声ガイドも収録させていただきましたー！
In collaboration with The National Gallery in London, I also recorded an audio guide!
すごーい！
Incredible!
しかも、こちらね、なんと、らでんの公式チャンネルにてアップする
Moreover, this is actually scheduled to be uploaded
予定でございますが、
onto Raden's official channel,
詳細は後日公開予定となりますので、続報をお待ちくださーい！
but details will be announced later, so please stay tuned for updates!
と、グッズとガイドと盛り沢山なんですが、
So with both the merch and the guide, there's plenty in store,
みんな、ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリー、どんなとこか…ごめんなさい
but everyone, what kind of place The National Gallery in London is... sorry!
ちょっと待って。ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリー、どんなところか、気になりませんか？
Wait a second. Aren't you curious what The National Gallery in London is like?
ロンドンの街並み、見てみたくないですか？
Don't you want to see what London looks like?
ということで！なんと、実は！
And so! Believe it or not...
ReGLOSSメンバーで、ロンドンロケに行ってきましたー！
The ReGLOSS members went on location to London!
そのロケの様子はReGLOSSチャンネルなどで後日公開予定と
Footage from the trip is scheduled to be released later on the ReGLOSS channel,
なっておりますので、こちらもぜひお楽しみにー！
so please look forward to that as well!
ということで、重大告知その2は
And with that, Major Announcement #2 was
儒烏風亭らでんとロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボでございました！ありがとうー！
the collaboration between Juufuutei Raden and The National Gallery, London! Thank you!
そして今、えー、スタッフさんの方から…
And right now, from the staff...
え、どうやら今、Xで…これXですか？Xでトレンド2位だそうです！
Apparently right now on X—is this X?—we're trending at #2!
すごーい！みんなありがとー！
Awesome! Thank you, everyone!
大丈夫かな？トレンドに入った理由がらでんちゃんの体力が心配ですでめっちゃ入ってたらどうしようかな？
I wonder if it's okay? What if it's trending just because everyone is worried about my stamina?
でも今日は！今日は、もう体力がすっからかんになって次の日動けなくなるまで頑張るってらでんは決めたんです！
But today! Today, I've decided to give it my all until my stamina is completely drained and I can't move tomorrow!
だから今日はみんなもね、いっぱい、いっぱい楽しんでほしいです！
So I want all of you to have tons and tons of fun today!
どうですか、皆さん？ついてこれてますかー？
How is it, everyone? Can you keep up?!
あ、待ってくださいね。重大発表、まだあるんです！
Ah, wait a minute! There are still more major announcements!
まだあるんです、これで終わりじゃないんですよー！
There's still more—this isn't the end yet!
しかも、ライブもまだまだ続きますので、皆さんチャンネルはそのままですよ！
Plus, the live show is still going on, so keep your channels right where they are!
では、次の曲に行きたいと思いまーす！
Now then, let's head into the next song!
それでは、どうぞ！
Here we go!
水面に 映った藍
The indigo reflected on the water's surface
眩しく揺れる
sways brilliantly.
手探りで 探してた
Fumbling around, I searched for
足りない私
the incomplete parts of me.
ゆっくりと 動き出した
Slowly, it began to move,
何万年も前から
as if from tens of thousands of years ago,
この時を約束されていた
this very moment had been promised,
みたいに ほら
just look.
風は歌い 雨は語り
The wind sings, the rain speaks,
たどり着くよ
and we will reach
光のすみかへ
the abode of light.
幾重にも 重なってる
Layer upon layer,
この 地球の偶然
this Earth's coincidences intertwine.
影の向こう
Beyond the shadows,
真実の
the true
色 見つけ出すよ
colors will be found.
光のすみか
In the abode of light,
一つでも 欠けていたら
if even a single piece were missing,
きっと 出逢えて なかったね
we surely never would have met.
飛べぬまま 見上げてた
Unable to fly, I looked up
透明な空から
from the transparent sky...
From the clear, transparent sky,
真っ直ぐに差し込んだ
shining straight down...
優しい朝日
...is the gentle morning sun.
過ぎた季節がいびつに
As the past seasons distortedly...
削った今という瞬き
...carved away this blink of an eye called "now,"
どこにも同じものはないの
there is nothing quite the same anywhere.
ほら 生きてる証
Look, that is proof that we are alive.
風は歌い
The wind sings,
雨は語り
the rain speaks,
たどり着くよ
and we will reach...
光のすみかへ
...the dwelling of light.
幾重にも重なってる
Layered upon layer,
この地球の
on this Earth...
偶然
...by coincidence,
影の向こう
beyond the shadows,
真実の色
the true colors,
見つけ出すよ
we will find them.
光のすみかを
The dwelling of light.
一つでも
If even a single piece...
欠けていたら
...had been missing,
きっと出会えてなかったね
we surely would never have met.
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんは！
Good evening to everyone watching the live stream!
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここで、らでんの小噺 美術解説のお時間でーす！
We're in the middle of the concert, but it's time for Raden's Art Commentary corner!
今回ご紹介するのはこちらでーん！じゃーん！
Here's what I'll be introducing today! Ta-da!
フィンセント・ファン・ゴッホ『ひまわり』！
Vincent van Gogh's "Sunflowers"!
今回、ナショナル・ギャラリーさんより画像をお借りしておりますー！ありがとうございます！
We are borrowing the image from the National Gallery this time! Thank you very much!
ゴッホと言えば『ひまわり』というイメージを持っている方も少なくないのではないでしょうか。
When you think of Van Gogh, many of you probably think of "Sunflowers," right?
それもそのはず。実はゴッホの描いた『ひまわり』は1つだけじゃないんです。
And for good reason. Actually, the "Sunflowers" Van Gogh painted wasn't just one painting.
この世界に失われたものも含めて、7つの『ひまわり』があったんですよ。
Including the one that was lost to the world, there were actually seven "Sunflowers" paintings!
さて、では実際に作品をじっくり見てみましょうー！
Now, let's take a closer look at the actual artwork!
みんなはどんな感想を持ったかなー？
What kind of impression did everyone get?
改めて見ると、いろんなことが見えてきます。
When you look closely at it again, many things begin to stand out.
よく見ると、ひまわりの花の向きはバラバラで、花びらも不揃いですね。
If you look closely, the sunflowers are facing all different directions, and their petals are uneven.
しかし、温かな黄色が画面全体を包み込むことで、どこか生命力があふれているようにも見えませんか？
However, with the warm yellow enveloping the whole canvas, doesn't it seem to overflow with vitality?
ここからは、ゴッホと黄色、そしてゴッホとひまわりについて紐解いていきましょう。
From here, let's unpack Van Gogh and yellow, as well as Van Gogh and sunflowers.
「太陽は淡い硫黄の輝きを伝達するのだ」という言葉を残しているゴッホは、太陽の光を黄色で表現しました。
Van Gogh, who left the words "The sun conveys a pale yellow glow of sulfur," expressed sunlight through yellow.
そして黄色はゴッホにとって生命力の象徴でもあります。
And to Van Gogh, yellow was also a symbol of vitality.
この絵を描いた時、彼はフランス南部のアルルという街で心機一転、画家として仲間と頑張っていこうと意気込んでいました。
When he painted this, he was in Arles in southern France, enthusiastic about making a fresh start and working hard as a painter with his peers.
そんな気持ちを黄色に託したのかもしれません。
Perhaps he poured those feelings into the color yellow.
一方で、この絵のモチーフになっているひまわりについて見てみましょう。
On the other hand, let's look at the sunflowers that serve as the motif of this painting.
ひまわりは太陽に向かって咲きます。
Sunflowers bloom facing towards the sun.
太陽は西洋美術史において「神」を象徴します。
In Western art history, the sun symbolizes "God."
それに向かって咲くひまわりは、崇拝、従順、忠誠、そして信仰心や愛を象徴します。
Sunflowers blooming towards it symbolize adoration, obedience, loyalty, faith, and love.
ここでさらに遠回りして、彼の過去について知っていきましょう。
Now let's take a bit of a detour and learn about his past.
先ほどゴッホがアルルでの生活を始めた時、私は「心機一転」という表現をしました。
Earlier, when talking about Van Gogh starting his life in Arles, I used the phrase "making a fresh start."
実は彼、元々は牧師さんになりたかったんです。
Actually, he originally wanted to become a pastor.
彼は頑張って勉強や奉仕活動に注力しますが、上手くいきませんでした。
He studied hard and devoted himself to missionary work, but things did not go well.
画家への転身は、牧師さんへの道を断たれた後のことだったんですね。
His turning into a painter happened after his path to becoming a pastor was cut off.
そんな彼が描く信仰の象徴であるひまわり。
Thus, the sunflowers painted by him as a symbol of faith...
皆様はどう読み解きますか？
...how do you interpret them?
未来への希望の光？それとも自分への失望？
A light of hope toward the future? Or disappointment in himself?
ゴッホの見た光のすみかは、ひまわりにあったのかもしれませんね。
Perhaps the dwelling of light that Van Gogh saw was within the sunflowers.
という感じでございまして、こちらもロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんにて見ることができます！
And that's the story—you can also see this piece at The National Gallery in London!
ぜひぜひ行ってみてくださいーい！
Please be sure to go check it out!
あ、私かい
Oh, it's my turn?
はい！ということで、早いもので次が最後の曲でございますが…
Alright! And with that, time really flies, and this next one is our final song, but...
なんと！儒烏風亭らでん、
Amazingly! Juufuutei Raden...
新曲をリリースしまーす！
...is releasing a new song!
イェーイ！特報！でーん！新曲リリース！
Yay! Breaking news, ta-da! New song release!
タイトルは、「Miracle Palette」！
The title is: "Miracle Palette"!
はい、えーこちらですね、楽曲リリースなんですが、5月18日の0時00分…
Yes! So about this song release, it will be on May 18th at 00:00...
まあなので、今日の日付が変わったタイミングでリリースされます！
which means, it'll be released right when the date changes tonight!
5月18日といえば、そう！皆さん大正解！国際博物館の日でございますー！
Speaking of May 18th, yes! You're all spot on! It's International Museum Day!
そんなね、特別な日にリリース！
Releasing on such a special day!
そして、この配信が終わってすぐ！MVですね、なんとミュージックビデオが公開されます！
And right after this stream ends, the MV—that's right, a music video will premiere!
儒烏風亭らでん初のダンスてんこ盛り3DMVとなっておりますー！
It's Juufuutei Raden's very first 3D MV packed full of dancing!
そして、こちら楽曲コンセプトはジャズっぽい感じになっておりますー！
And the musical concept has a wonderful jazzy feel!
ということで、
So with that,
今から、ライブバージョンの「Miracle Palette」を披露したいと思います！
right now, I'd like to perform the live version of "Miracle Palette"!
ダンサーさんカモーーーン！
Dancers, come ooon!
よろしくお願いしまーす！
Looking forward to it!
お願いしまーす！
Thank you so much!
はい！来てくれてありがとうございます！
Yes! Thank you so much for joining us!
では、聴いてください、「Miracle Palette」。
Now then, please listen to: "Miracle Palette".
暗がりステージに立つ 雨傘を携え
Standing on a darkened stage, carrying an umbrella,
朧に霞む構図 印象 儚く
A vaguely hazy composition, an ephemeral impression.
始めましょ 雨粒ドローイング
Let us begin our raindrop drawing,
キャンヴァスはこの空、この世界
The canvas is this sky, this world!
Hop Hop 飛び回る
Hop, hop, leaping all around,
Tap Tap 打ち鳴らす
Tap, tap, tapping out the beat,
Dance Dance ぐるぐる
Dance, dance, round and round,
いざ ショータイム
Now, it's showtime!
Ladies and Gentlemen, Welcome to our magical show!
スポットライトを浴びて 輝きを放つ
Basking in the spotlight, radiating brilliance.
エンタシスよりプリズム 分光をスタンバイ
From entasis to prism, preparing the spectrum standby.
この鈍色の空に 七色の橋を架けて見せましょう
Across this lead-gray sky, let me build a rainbow bridge for you.
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！
Come now, feast your eyes upon this!
目に映るもの、今を彩るから
Because everything reflected in your eyes will color the present.
大きな絵筆で描き出す 大胆なパースの中
Sketching out with a giant paintbrush within bold perspectives,
鳴呼 びしょ濡れの舞台は ミラクルなパレット
Ah, this drenched stage is a miraculous palette!
マスカレイドな第二部の開演
Curtain rises on Act Two, a masquerade—
Shall we dance?
モノトーンから極彩色に
From monotone into vivid hues,
アシンメトリーなグラデーションで
With an asymmetrical gradation,
夢中になってほしいの
I want you to be completely captivated.
雨雲にマーブリング
Marbling across the rainclouds,
目を奪われたその隙
While your eyes are dazzled,
イリュージョンをスタンバイ
Setting the illusion on standby.
ところで皆さん、なくし物はございませんか？
By the way, everyone, haven't you lost something?
どなた様もおいでませ！
Welcome, one and all!
あの手この手で魅了していくから
I'll enchant you with every trick in the book!
一足お先に まんまと
One step ahead, effortlessly,
盗みだすわ あなたの心を
I will steal your heart away!
光を放ち出す きらめきのパレット
Unleashing radiant light, a glittering palette!
さてさて！いよいよ大詰め、クライマックスに向けて盛り上がってまいりましょう！
Now then, now then! We're nearing the grand finale, let's get hyped for the climax!
Listen!
OK, 5・4・3・2・1 Go on the Show!
OK, 5, 4, 3, 2, 1, go on the show!
最大級のキャンヴァスに描き出す
Painting across the grandest canvas,
誰も見たことのない景色
A scenery no one has ever seen before.
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！
Come now, feast your eyes upon this!
次元の壁を超えて閃くから
Transcending dimensional walls, sparking with inspiration!
大きな絵筆で描き出す
Sketching out with a giant paintbrush...
大胆な パースの中 さあ
In this bold perspective, come on!
みんなで大団円 迎えに行こう
Let's all go welcome the grand finale!
嗚呼 びしょ濡れの舞台は ミラクルなパレット
Ah, this soaking wet stage is a miracle palette!
Woah...
[特報 その③]
[Special Report #3]
[新情報]
[New Information]
[箱根探訪編 DLC]
[Hakone Exploration Edition DLC]
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！ 目に映るもの、今を彩るから
Come now, take a good look! For I will color everything your eyes behold right now!
儒烏風亭らでんがご案内 ピクセルミュージアム
Juufuutei Raden Presents: Pixel Museum
追加ダウンロードコンテンツ 箱根探訪編 配信決定！
Additional DLC "Hakone Exploration Edition" has been confirmed for release!
イベント展示のご案内
An introduction to our event exhibition!
今回のテーマは... 箱根！
The theme this time is... Hakone!
らでん館長の大好きな箱根にまつわる作品をご用意！
Featuring artwork connected to Director Raden's beloved Hakone!
館内もイベント仕様で、箱根の魅力がたっぷりと詰まっています！
The museum interior is also styled for the event, packed with the charms of Hakone!
もちろん解説はフルボイスでお届けしますよ！
Of course, all commentary will be delivered with full voice acting!
儒烏風亭らでんがご案内 ピクセルミュージアム
Juufuutei Raden Presents: Pixel Museum
追加ダウンロードコンテンツ 箱根探訪編 2026年12月配信予定！
Additional DLC "Hakone Exploration Edition," scheduled for release in December 2026!
ちょっと待つだけね〜
Just wait a little while, okay?
な、な、なんと！
S-S-Surprise!
昨年6月5日の発売から1年を待たずに
Less than a year since its release on June 5th of last year...
『儒烏風亭らでんがご案内 ピクセルミュージアム』の追加ダウンロードコンテンツ、箱根探訪編の配信が決定しましたー！
the release of the "Hakone Exploration Edition" DLC for Juufuutei Raden Presents: Pixel Museum has been confirmed!
やったー！
Yay!
みんながね、いっぱいダウンロードしてくれて、みんながたくさん遊んでくれたおかげです。
It's all thanks to everyone downloading it and playing it so much!
本当にありがとうございますー！
Thank you all so very much!
今回の舞台は、皆様おなじみの箱根でございますー！
The stage this time is the familiar Hakone!
前作に引き続き、箱根ガラスの森美術館様に加え、
Following up on the previous work, in addition to the Hakone Venetian Glass Museum...
今回はなんと、ポーラ美術館様と小田急箱根様にもご協力いただけることとなりました！拍手〜！
we are thrilled to collaborate with the Pola Museum of Art and Odakyu Hakone as well! Round of applause!
館長のプライベートルームもイベント仕様にアップデート！
The Director's private room is also updated for the event!
箱根の魅力マシマシでお届けいたしますよ〜！いいでしょう〜！
We'll bring you extra helpings of Hakone's charm! Isn't that great?
そんな追加ダウンロードコンテンツ箱根探訪編は、2026年12月に配信予定！
That DLC, "Hakone Exploration Edition," is scheduled for release in December 2026!
早速ですね、来週5月23日、24日に京都にて開催されますBitSummitにラデピクも登場！
And right away, Radepic will be featured at BitSummit held in Kyoto on May 23rd and 24th next week!
大好評発売中のラデピクの試遊や、箱根探訪編のキービジュアルポストカードの配布もあるみたいですよ〜！
There will be play demos of the hit game Radepic, and they'll even be giving out Hakone Exploration Edition key visual postcards!
詳しい情報は公式ホームページとジュピターさんの公式Xを要チェックです！
Be sure to check the official website and Jupiter's official X account for detailed info!
まだまだ嬉しい情報もあるかも〜！
There might be even more exciting news in store!
それではリリースまでお楽しみに〜！
So look forward to the release!
はい！そして、そして！皆さんお待たせね！
All right! And next, next! Everyone's been waiting!
儒烏風亭らでん、100万人記念グッズが発売されまーす！
Juufuutei Raden's 1 Million Subscriber Commemorative Merchandise is going on sale!
ごめんね、今日本当に何かいっぱい発表が多くて（笑）
Sorry, there are just so many announcements today!
早速詳細を見ていきましょう。1つ目はこちら！デン！
Let's check out the details right away. First up is this! Ta-da!
「新衣装でライブ！アクリルブロック」...いや、めっちゃ疲れてるらでんが映ってた（笑）
"Live in New Outfit! Acrylic Block"... Wait, a totally exhausted Raden was on screen!
「新衣装でライブ！アクリルブロック！」
"Live in New Outfit! Acrylic Block!"
ライブステージで楽しそうに歌う新衣装のらでん、森倉円先生の描き下ろしでございます！いいでしょう〜！
Raden singing happily in her new outfit on the live stage, drawn by Morikura En-sensei! Isn't it wonderful?
こちらアクリルブロックの表裏に印刷されておりまして、めっちゃね、奥行きが感じられるものとなってるんですよ〜
It's printed on both the front and back of the acrylic block, giving it an amazing sense of depth!
続いてはこちら！デン！
Next up is this! Ta-da!
はい！「らでんの衣装いろいろ3連アクリルキーホルダー」！
Yes! "Raden's Outfits Galore 3-Piece Acrylic Keychain"!
新衣装、通常衣装、flashpoint衣装の3種類の3連連結アクリルキーホルダーとなっております！
It's a connected 3-piece acrylic keychain featuring three outfits: New, Default, and Flashpoint!
イラストは、心パズルリズムの時にお馴染み、ちぽみるく先生でございます〜！
The illustrations are by Chipomilk-sensei, known from Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm!
続いてはこちら！デン！
Next up is this! Ta-da!
「新衣装モチーフピンバッジセット」！新衣装をモチーフにしたピンバッジセットですよ〜
"New Outfit Motif Pin Badge Set"! It's a pin badge set themed after my new outfit!
懐中時計、それから今はしてないけどマスク、シルクハット、モノクルの4種類となっております〜
It includes 4 types: pocket watch, a mask (which I'm not wearing now), top hat, and monocle!
続いてはこちら！デン！
Next up is this! Ta-da!
「ライブ前のトラブル!? ボイス」！
"Trouble Before the Live Performance!? Voice Pack"!
らでんが書き下ろした台本です！どんなトラブルが...
I wrote the script myself! Just what kind of trouble...
...るのかは聞いてみてのお楽しみー
...what it's like, look forward to hearing it!
そしてフルセット購入特典はこちら！デン！
And here is the bonus for purchasing the full set! Ta-da!
はい、え、儒烏風亭らでん直筆サイン入り森倉円先生描き下ろしポストカード！
Yes, a postcard newly illustrated by Morikura En-sensei, autographed by Jufutei Raden!
今回も購入していただいた方全員に直筆でサインを書かせていただきますよ！
This time again, I will personally hand-sign for everyone who purchases it!
皆さんに届くように精一杯書かせていただくので、よろしくお願いいたしますー！
I'll put my heart into signing every one so it reaches you, so please look forward to it!
さらに特典ボイスもつきます！こちらもらでんが書き下ろしてますー！
In addition, you get a bonus voice track! Raden wrote this script as well!
はい！ということで、もう今日ね、すごい盛りだくさんでございましたが、
Yes! So, today was truly packed with so much content, but...
皆さん追いつけてますか？
are you all keeping up?
もう結構とんでもないね、発表をたくさんしたんですけれども、
We made quite a lot of crazy announcements today,
らでんが一番結構とんでもないなと思っておりますー！
but I think Raden herself finds it the craziest!
ということで本日の重大発表は、その1、東京国立博物館さんとのコラボ！
So, today's major announcements: Number 1, a collab with Tokyo National Museum!
その2、ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボ！
Number 2, a collab with The National Gallery, London!
その3、儒烏風亭らでんがご案内 Pixel Museum DLC発売決定でございます！
Number 3, the Pixel Museum DLC guided by Jufutei Raden is confirmed for release!
情報量がね、多すぎたと思うので、是非アーカイブでも確認してみてください！
There was so much info, so please be sure to check the archive stream as well!
そしてこの後はメン限でアンコールライブあります！
And after this, we'll have an encore live for members only!
その時にまた衣装はね、ゆっくりお見せしようかなと思っておりますので、
I'm planning to take time showing off the outfit properly then,
まだの方はチャンネル登録と、気になるよーっていう方は、
so please subscribe if you haven't, and if you're curious,
メンバーでね、またアンコールライブでお会いしましょー！
join the membership, and let's meet again at the encore live!
そしてそして！忘れちゃいけません！この後すぐ新曲MV公開でございます！
And, and! Don't forget! Right after this, the new song's MV will premiere!
頑張って作ったんで、いっぱい見てほしいですー！
We worked really hard on it, so I hope you watch it a lot!
はい！
Yes!
ということでございまして、日頃応援してくださっている皆々様、
And so, to everyone who always supports me,
見ていただいている、聴いていただいているリスナーの皆様のおかげで、
and all the listeners watching and listening, thanks to all of you,
今回ね、このライブを開催することができました！
I was able to hold this live stream today!
本当に本当にありがとうございます！とっても嬉しいです！
Thank you so, so very much! I'm truly happy!
これからもね、歌もね、ダンスも、自分のね、やりたいことも、
Moving forward, with singing, dancing, and everything I want to do,
いっぱい頑張っていきますので、是非応援の程よろしくお願いいたします！
I'll keep working as hard as I can, so please continue to support me!
それでは！メン限アンコールライブでお会いいたしましょう！
Well then! Let's meet again in the member-only encore live!
本日のお相手は私、儒烏風亭らでんでございました！
Your host today was me, Jufutei Raden!
それでは皆さん、良い夜をお過ごしください！
With that, everyone, please have a wonderful night!
さようならでーーん！
Sayona-Raden!